As you pointed out, every time you come here, you learn something.
كما أشرتم، كلما أتى أحدكم إلى هنا، تعلم شيئاً جديداً.
This morning, the world's experts
صباح اليوم، خبراء العالم،
from I guess three or four different companies on building seats,
من ثلاث أو أربع شركات مختلفة، في بناء الكراسي،
I think concluded that ultimately, the solution is, people shouldn't sit down.
أعتقد أنهم استنتجوا، أن الحل هو، أن يتوقف الناس عن الجلوس.
I could have told them that.
كان يمكنني أن أقول ذلك لهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yesterday, the automotive guys gave us some new insights.
بالأمس، أعطانا خبراء السيارات بعض وجهات النظر الجديدة.
They pointed out that, I believe it was between 30 and 50 years from today,
أشاروا، وكان ذلك ما بين 30 و50 سنة من الآن،
they will be steering cars by wire,
بأنهم سيقودون سياراتهم بالأسلاك،
without all that mechanical stuff.
من غير أجزاء ميكانيكية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's reassuring.
هذا مطمئن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
They then pointed out that there'd be, sort of, the other controls by wire,
ثم أشاروا إلى وسائل تحكم عن طريق الأسلاك،
to get rid of all that mechanical stuff.
للتخلص من الأجزاء الميكانيكية.
That's pretty good, but why not get rid of the wires?
ذلك جيد جداً، ولكن لماذا لا نتخلص من الأسلاك؟
Then you don't need anything to control the car, except thinking about it.
عندها لن نحتاج لأي شيء للتحكم بالسيارة، ما عدا التفكير في ذلك.
I would love to talk about the technology,
أوّد الحديث عن التقنية،
and sometime, in what's past the 15 minutes,
وأحياناً، فيما يتعدى 15 دقيقة،
I'll be happy to talk to all the techno-geeks around here
سأكون سعيداً بالحديث مع كل المهووسيين بالتقنية هنا
about what's in here.
عن ما يوجد هنا.
But if I had one thing to say about this, before we get to first,
ولكن إن كان لدي شيء واحد لأقوله عن هذا، قبل أن نصل إلى الأول،
it would be that from the time we started building this,
فسيكون أنه أننا منذ أن بدأنا في صنع هذا،
the big idea wasn't the technology.
الفكرة الكبيرة لم تكن التقنية.
It really was a big idea in technology when we started applying it
كانت فكرة كبيرة في التقنية حين بدأنا بتطبيقها
in the iBOT for the disabled community.
على جهاز آي بوت iBOT لأفراد المجتمع المعاقين.
The big idea here is, I think, a new piece of a solution
الفكرة الكبيرة هي، على ما أعتقد، هي جزء جديد من حل
to a fairly big problem in transportation.
لمشكلة كبيرة جداً في مجال المواصلات.
And maybe to put that in perspective: there's so much data on this,
وربما، لنضع الأمور في نصابها: هناك الكثير من البيانات عن ذلك،
I'll be happy to give it to you in different forms.
سأكون سعيداً بإعطائكم إياها بأشكال مختلفة.
You never know what strikes the fancy of whom,
لا نعلم أبداً ما سيعجب من،
but everybody is perfectly willing to believe the car changed the world.
ولكن الجميع مستعد للتصديق بأن السيارة غيّرت العالم
And Henry Ford, just about 100 years ago, started cranking out Model Ts.
وهينري فورد، قبل 100 سنة، بدأ بإنتاج مودل تي.
What I don't think most people think about
ما لا أعتقد أن الناس تفكر فيه
is the context of how technology is applied.
هو السياق الذي تُطَبَقُ فيه التقنية.
For instance, in that time, 91 percent of America
فعلى سبيل المثال، في ذلك العصر، 91 بالمائة من سكان أمريكا
lived either on farms or in small towns.
كانوا يعيشون في المزارع أو في قرى صغيرة
So, the car --
إذاً، السيارة --
the horseless carriage that replaced the horse and carriage -- was a big deal;
العربة التي لا تحتاج لحصان والتي حلّت محل العربة والحصان -- كانت مسألة كبيرة؛
it went twice as fast as a horse and carriage.
كانت سرعتها ضعف سرعة العربة والحصان.
It was half as long.
كان طولها نصف طول العربة والحصان.
And it was an environmental improvement, because, for instance,
وكانت تحسيناً بيئياً، لأنه على سبيل المثال،
in 1903 they outlawed horses and buggies in downtown Manhattan,
في 1903 تم منع الخيول والعربات من دخول مانهاتن،
because you can imagine what the roads look like
والسبب، يمكننا تخيّل منظر الشوارع
when you have a million horses,
حين يكون لديك ملايين الخيول،
and a million of them urinating and doing other things,
وهذه الملايين تتبول وتفعل أشياءً أخرى،
and the typhoid and other problems created were almost unimaginable.
والتيفويد والأمراض الأخرى الناتجة عن ذلك لا تخطر في البال.
So the car was the clean environmental alternative to a horse and buggy.
إذاً، السيارة كانت البديل النظيف بيئياً للعربة والحصان.
It also was a way for people to get from their farm to a farm,
وكانت السيارة أيضاً وسيلة لانتقال الناس من مزرعة إلى مزرعة،
or their farm to a town, or from a town to a city.
أو من مزارعهم إلى القرى، أو من القرى إلى المدن.
It all made sense, with 91 percent of the people living there.
كان الأمر واضحاً، مع وجود 91% من السكان في المزارع أو القرى.
By the 1950s, we started connecting all the towns together
ولكن في الخمسينيات، بدأنا بوصل القرى ببعضها البعض
with what a lot of people claim is the eighth wonder of the world, the highway system.
بما يدّعي الكثير من الناس بأنه ثامن عجائب الدنيا، شبكة الطرق السريعة.
And it is certainly a wonder.
وهي فعلاً من عجائب الدنيا.
And by the way, as I take shots at old technologies,
وعلى فكرة، حين أنتقد التقنيات القديمة،
I want to assure everybody, and particularly the automotive industry --
أريد أن أؤكد للجميع، وخصوصاً صناعة السيارات --
who's been very supportive of us --
التي كانت تساندنا --
that I don't think this in any way competes with airplanes, or cars.
لا أعتقد أن هذا ينافس الطائرات أو السيارات في أي شيء.
But think about where the world is today.
ولكني أفكر في مكان العالم اليوم.
50 percent of the global population now lives in cities.
50% من سكان العالم يعيشون في المدن الآن.
That's 3.2 billion people.
وعدد سكان العالم 3.2 مليار نسمة.
We've solved all the transportation problems
لقد حللنا كل مشاكلنا المتعلقة بالمواصلات
that have changed the world to get it to where we are today.
والتي غيرت العالم إلى ما نحن عليه اليوم.
500 years ago, sailing ships started getting reliable enough;
قبل 500 عام، أصبحت السفن معتمدة بما فيه الكفاية؛
we found a new continent.
وجدنا قارة جديدة.
150 years ago, locomotives got efficient enough, steam power,
قبل 150 عاماً، أصبحت القطارات معتمدة بما فيه الكفاية، الطاقة البخارية،
that we turned the continent into a country.
لدرجة أننا حولنا القارة (الجديدة) إلى دولة.
Over the last hundred years, we started building cars,
خلال المئة عام الأخيرة، بدأنا في صناعة السيارات،
and then over the 50 years we've connected every city to every other city
وبعد ذلك، ربطنا المدن ببعضها خلال نصف قرن
in an extraordinarily efficient way,
بطريقة فعالة جداً،
and we have a very high standard of living as a consequence of that.
ونتمتع بأسلوب معيشة عالٍ نتيجة لذلك.
But during that entire process, more and more people have been born,
ولكن خلال هذه العملية برمتها، ولد المزيد من الناس،
and more and more people are moving to cities.
وانتقل المزيد من الناس إلى المدن.
China alone is going to move four to six hundred million people
الصين لوحدها ستنقل ما بين أربعمائة إلى ستمائة ملايين نسمة
into cities in the next decade and a half.
إلى المدن في الخمس عشرة سنة القادمة.
And so, nobody, I think, would argue that airplanes, in the last 50 years,
ولذلك، لا أحد، باعتقادي، سيجادل في أن الطائرات، في نصف القرن الماضي،
have turned the continent and the country now into a neighborhood.
قد حولت القارة والدولة اليوم إلى حي صغير.
And if you just look at how technology has been applied,
وحين تنظرون إلى التقنيات التي طبِّقَت،
we've solved all the long-range, high-speed, high-volume,
ستجدون أننا حلنا كل ما هو على المدى البعيد، ويسير بسرعة هائلة، وذا حجم كبير،
large-weight problems of moving things around.
وذا ثقل شديد من المشاكل المتعلقة بنقل الأشياء هنا وهناك.
Nobody would want to give them up.
لن يستغني عن هذه الحلول أحد.
And I certainly wouldn't want to give up my airplane,
وبالتأكيد، لن استغني أبداً عن طائرتي الخاصة،
or my helicopter, or my Humvee, or my Porsche.
ولا طائرتي العمودية، ولا سيارتي الهامر، ولا سيارتي البورش.
I love them all. I don't keep any of them in my living room.
أحبهم جميعاً. ولا أحتفظ بأيٍ منها في صالة منزلي.
The fact is, the last mile is the problem,
في الحقيقة، الميل الأخير هو المشكلة،
and half the world now lives in dense cities.
ونصف العالم يعيش في مدن مزدحمة.
And people spend, depending on who they are,
ويصرف الناس، حسب مكان إقامتهم،
between 90 and 95 percent of their energy getting around on foot.
ما بين 90 إلى 95 من طاقتهم للتنقل مشياً.
I think there's -- I don't know what data would impress you,
أعتقد أن هناك -- لا أدري أي الإحصائيات ستعجبكم،
but how about, 43 percent of the refined fuel produced in the world
ولكن ما رأيكم، 43% من الوقود المكرر الذي ينتجه العالم
is consumed by cars in metropolitan areas in the United States.
تستهلكه السيارات في التجمعات الحضرية في الولايات المتحدة.
Three million people die every year in cities due to bad air,
3 ملايين إنسان يموتون كل عام في المدن من جرّاء الهواء الملوّث،
and almost all particulate pollution on this planet
وتقريباً كل التلوّث الجزيئي على هذا الكوكب
is produced by transportation devices, particularly sitting in cities.
ناتج عن أجهزة المواصلات، خصوصاً تلك القابعة في المدن.
And again, I say that not to attack any industry,
مرة أخرى، أقول لكم أنني لا أنوي الهجوم على أي صناعة،
I think -- I really do -- I love my airplane,
أعتقد أنني -- بل أنني فعلاً -- أحب طائرتي الخاصة،
and cars on highways moving 60 miles an hour
والسيارات على الطرق السريعة تسير بسرعة 60 ميل (96.5 كيلومتر) في الساعة
are extraordinarily efficient,
ولها كفاءة استثنائية،
both from an engineering point of view,
من ناحية هندسية،
an energy consumption point of view, and a utility point of view.
ومن ناحية استهلاك الطاقة، ومن ناحية المنفعة.
And we all love our cars, and I do.
وكلنا نحب السيارات، وأنا أحبها أيضاً.
The problem is, you get into the city and you want to go four blocks,
المشكلة هي، حين تصل إلى مدينة وتريد أن تسير مسافة أربع مربوعات،
it's neither fun nor efficient nor productive.
لن تستمتع ولن تكون فعّالاً ولا منتجاً.
It's not sustainable.
إنها عملية غير مستدامة.
If -- in China, in the year 1998, 417 million people used bicycles;
لو -- في الصين، في عام 1998، كان 417 مليون نسمة يكتفون بالدراجة؛
1.7 million people used cars.
و1.7 مليون نسمة يستخدمون السيارة.
If five percent of that population became, quote, middle class,
لو تحوّل 5% من هؤلاء الناس إلى ما يسمى طبقة وسطى،
and wanted to go the way we've gone in the last hundred years
وأرادوا أن يقتدوا بما فعلناه منذ قرن
at the same time that 50 percent of their population are moving into cities
في حين أن 50% من السكان ينتقلون إلى مدن
of the size and density of Manhattan, every six weeks --
بحجم وكثافة مانهاتن، كل ستة أسابيع --
it isn't sustainable environmentally;
فإن هذا لن يكون مستداماً من الناحية البيئية،
it isn't sustainable economically -- there just ain't enough oil --
ولن يكون مستداماً من الناحية الاقتصادية -- فالنفط المتوفر لن يكفيهم.
and it's not sustainable politically.
ولن يكون مستداماً من الناحية السياسية.
I mean, what are we fighting over right now?
أعني، ما الذي نتحارب عليه الآن؟
We can make it complicated, but what's the world fighting over right now?
يمكننا أن نجعل الأمر معقداً، ولكن ما الذي يتقاتل العالم عليه الآن؟
So it seemed to me that somebody had to work on that last mile,
لذلك، بدا لا أن على أحدهم العمل على هذا الميل الأخير،
and it was dumb luck. We were working on iBOTs,
ويا لحظنا العاثر؛ كنا نعمل على الكرسي المتحرك المطوّر (آي بوت)
but once we made this, we instantly decided
ولكن في لحظة صنعنا لهذا الجهاز، قررنا عندها
it could be a great alternative to jet skis. You don't need the water.
أنه قد يكون بديلاً مناسباً للدراجة المائية. لسنا بحاجة للماء.
Or snowmobiles. You don't need the snow.
أو للسيارة الثلجية. لسنا بحاجة للثلج.
Or skiing. It's just fun, and people love to move around doing fun things.
أو للتزلج على الثلوج. إنه ممتع، والناس بحاجة للاستمتاع أثناء تنقلاتهم.
And every one of those industries, by the way --
ومن بين كل هذه الصناعات، بالمناسبة --
just golf carts alone is a multi-billion-dollar industry.
سيارات الغولف وحدها هي الصناعة التي تدر الملايين.
But rather than go license this off, which is what we normally do,
ولكن بدل أن نرخص هذا الاختراع لجهة أخرى، وهو ما نفعله عادةً،
it seemed to me that if we put all our effort not into the technology,
بدى لي أننا لو صرفنا كافة جهودنا ليس على التقنية ذاتها،
but into an understanding of a world that's solved all its other problems,
بل على فهم عالَمٍ تمكن من جل جميع مشاكله الأخرى،
but has somehow come to accept that cities -- which,
ولكنه بطريقة ما تقبّل أن المدن -- والتي
right back from ancient Greece on, were meant to walk around,
منذ عهد اليونان القديمة فما بعد ذلك، كُتِبَ عليها ألا تكون أكثر من ممشى،
cities that were architected and built for people --
مدنٌ عمّرَت وشيّدَت للناس --
now have a footprint that,
لديها الآن بصمة بيئية و ذلك،
while we've solved every other transportation problem --
بينما حللنا كل مشاكل النقل الأخرى --
and it's like Moore's law.
وهو وضع يشبه قانون مور.
I mean, look at the time it took to cross a continent in a Conestoga wagon,
أعني، انظروا كم الوقت استلزم الانتقال عبر قارة باستخدام عربة أمريكية من القرن التاسع عشر،
then on a railroad, then an airplane.
ثم على سكة الحديد، ثم على الطائرة.
Every other form of transportation's been improved.
جميع أشكال المواصلات تم تحسينها.
In 5,000 years, we've gone backwards in getting around cities.
خلال 5000 سنة، تخلفنا في التنقل داخل المدن.
They've gotten bigger; they're spread out.
لقد كبرت المدن وتوسعت.
The most expensive real estate on this planet in every city --
وأغلى العقارات على هذا الكوكب في كل مدينة --
Wilshire Boulevard, or Fifth Avenue, or Tokyo, or Paris --
شارع ويلشير بلوس أنجلس، أو الشارع الخامس في نيو يورك، أو طوكيو، أو باريس --
the most expensive real estate is their downtowns.
أغلى العقارات تقع في وسط هذه المدن.
65 percent of the landmass of our cities are parked cars.
65% من المساحة الأرضية لمدننا تشغلها سيارات واقفة.
The 20 largest cities in the world.
في أكبر عشرين مدينة في العالم.
So you wonder, what if cities could give to their pedestrians
فلكم أن تتساؤلوا، ماذا لو قدّمت المدن لمشاتها
what we take for granted as we now go between cities?
ما اعتدنا عليه حين نتنقل بين المدن؟
What if you could make them fun, attractive, clean,
ماذا لو استطعنا أن نجعل ذلك ممتعاً، وجذّاباً، ونظيفاً،
environmentally friendly?
وصديقاً للبيئة؟
What if it would make it a little bit more palatable
ماذا لو جعلت هذه الآلة الأمور أكثر استساغة
to have access via this, as that last link to mass transit,
لأن يكون لدينا عن طريقها آخر صلة بالنقل الجماعي،
to get out to your cars so we can all live in the suburbs
لنخرج من سياراتنا لنعيش جميعاً في مناطق حضرية
and use our cars the way we want,
ونستخدم سياراتنا بالطريقة التي نريد،
and then have our cities energized again?
ونجعل مدننا مفعمة بالطاقة من جديد؟
We thought it would be really neat to do that,
فكرنا بأن فعل ذلك سيكون جميلاً،
and one of the problems we really were worried about
وأحد المشاكل التي أقلقتنا
is: how do we get legal on the sidewalk?
هي، كيف سيسمح لنا قانونياً بالقيادة على الرصيف،
Because technically I've got motors; I've got wheels -- I'm a motor vehicle.
لأننا فنياً لدينا محركات، لدينا عجلات -- أنا مركبة بمحرك.
I don't look like a motor vehicle.
قد لا أبدو مثل مركبة بمحرك.
I have the same footprint as a pedestrian;
لدي آثار أقدام كشخص يمشي،
I have the same unique capability
لدي قدرة مميزة
to deal with other pedestrians in a crowded space.
للتعامل مع المشاة في مكان مزدحم.
I took this down to Ground Zero,
أخذت هذه إلى جراوند زيرو،
and knocked my way through crowds for an hour.
وواصلت سيري عبر الجمع لمدة ساعة.
I'm a pedestrian. But the law typically lags technology by a generation or two,
أنا ماشي. ولكن القانون ابطأ من التقنية بجيل أو جيلين،
and if we get told we don't belong on the sidewalk, we have two choices.
وحين يقال لنا ألا مكان لنا على الرصيف، فسيكون لدينا خيارين.
We're a recreational vehicle that doesn't really matter,
نحن مركبة تسلية ليست بتلك الأهمية،
and I don't spend my time doing that kind of stuff.
ولا أقضي وقتي أفعل مثل هذه الأشياء.
Or maybe we should be out in the street
أو ربما علينا أن نكون في الشارع
in front of a Greyhound bus or a vehicle.
أمام باص جريهاوند أو مركبة أخرى.
We've been so concerned about that,
كنا شديدي الاهتمام بذلك،
we went to the Postmaster General of the United States,
ذهبنا إلى أكبر مسؤول عن البريد في الولايات المتحدة،
as the first person we ever showed on the outside,
كأول شخص نريه اختراعنا في الخارج،
and said, "Put your people on it. Everybody trusts their postman.
وقلنا، "ضعوا موظفيكم عليها، الكل يثق بساعي البريد.
And they belong on the sidewalks, and they'll use it seriously."
ومكانهم الرصيف، وسيستخدمونها جدياً."
He agreed. We went to a number of police departments
وافقنا الرأي. ذهبنا إلى عدد من أقسام الشرطة
that want their police officers back in the neighborhood
التي تريد عودة رجالها في المجتمع
on the beat, carrying 70 pounds of stuff. They love it.
حاملين 70 رطلاً من الأشياء. أحبوا هذه الفكرة.
And I can't believe a policeman is going to give themselves a ticket.
ولا أعتقد أن رجال الشرطة سيعطون أنفسهم مخالفات مرورية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we've been working really, really hard,
لذلك، عملنا بجدية،
but we knew that the technology would not be as hard to develop
ولكننا نعلم أن إنتاج التكنلوجيا ليس أصعب
as an attitude about what's important, and how to apply the technology.
من خلق الموقف المناسب مما هو مهم، وكيفية تطبيق التكنولوجيا.
We went out and we found some visionary people
بحثنا ووجدنا أشخاص يملكون رؤية
with enough money to let us design and build these things,
وما يكفي من المال لتصميم وبناء هذه الأشياء
and in hopefully enough time to get them accepted.
والوقت الكافي ليقبلها الناس.
So, I'm happy, really, I am happy to talk about this technology as much as you want.
لهذا السبب، أنا فعلاً مسرور. أنا مسرور بالحديث عن هذه التقنية كما تريدون.
And yes, it's really fun, and yes, you should all go out and try it.
ونعم، الأمر ممتع جداً، ونعم، عليكم جميعاً أن تجربوا.
But if I could ask you to do one thing,
ولكن لو طلبت منكم أمراً واحداً،
it's not to think about it as a piece of technology,
وهو آلا تفكروا بها كقطعة من التقنية،
but just imagine that, although we all understand somehow
بل تخيلوا أن، بالرغم من أننا بشكلٍ ما نفهم
that it's reasonable that we use our 4,000-pound machine,
أنه من المعقول أننا نستخدم آلة تزن 4000 رطل،
which can go 60 miles an hour,
التي تسير 60 ميلاً في الساعة،
that can bring you everywhere you want to go,
وتأخذك أينما تريد،
and somehow it's also what we used for the last mile,
وبشكل ما، هي ما استخدمناه لنصل إلى الخطوة الأخيرة،
and it's broken, and it doesn't work.
وهي محطة، ولا تعمل.
One of the more exciting things that occurred to us
أحد الأشياء المثيرة التي حدثت لنا
about why it might get accepted, happened out here in California.
حول إن كانت ستقبل أم لا، حدث هنا في كاليفورنيا.
A few weeks ago, after we launched it,
قبل عدة أسابيع، بعد التدشين،
we were here with a news crew on Venice Beach, zipping up and back,
كنا هنا مع فريق أخباري على بحر فينيس، نتجول،
and he's marveling at the technology,
وأثناء انبهاره بالتقنية،
and meanwhile bicycles are zipping by,
وحينها كانت الدرجات تتجول بجانبنا،
and skateboarders are zipping by,
وألواح السكيتبورد تتجول بجانبنا،
and a little old lady -- I mean, if you looked in the dictionary,
وامرأة عجوز -- أقصد، حين تبحث في القاموس عن
a little old lady -- came by me --
امرأة عجوز -- مرت بجانبي --
and now that I'm on this, I'm the height of a normal adult now --
وأنا أركب هذه، وطولي كطول شخص طبيعي الآن --
and she just stops, and the camera is there, and she looks up at me
وتتوقف العجوز، والكاميرا موجودة، وتنظر إلي
and says, "Can I try that?"
وتقول، "أيمكنني أن أجرب هذا؟"
And what was I -- you know, how are you going to say anything?
وماذا كان علي -- أتعلمون، كيف يمكنني أن أقول شيئاً؟
And so I said, "Sure."
فقلت، "طبعاً"
So I get off, and she gets on, and with a little bit of the usual, ah,
فنزلت، وركبت هي، وكان الأمر طبيعياً قليلاً، آه،
then she turns around, and she goes about 20 feet,
ثم انعطفت، وابتعدت عني 20 قدماً،
and she turns back around, and she's all smiles.
ثم دارت، يعلو وجهها ابتسامة عريضة.
And she comes back to me and she stops, and she says,
ثم عادت إليّ ووقفت، وقالت،
"Finally, they made something for us."
"أخيراً، صنعوا شيئاً لنا."
And the camera is looking down at her.
والكاميرا تنظر إليها.
I'm thinking, "Wow, that was great --
وأنا أفكر، "يا للهول، كان ذلك عظيماً --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- please lady, don't say another word."
-- أرجوك يا سيدتي، لا تقولي كلمة أخرى."
And the camera is down at her,
والكاميرا موجهة عليها،
and this guy has to put the microphone in her face,
وقام أحد بوضع الميكروفون قرب وجهها،
said, "What do you mean by that?"
وقال، "ماذا تقصدين بذلك؟"
And I figured, "It's all over now,"
استنتجت أنا، "لقد انتهى كل شيء الآن،"
and she looks up and she says, "Well,"
ونظرت إلينا وقالت، "في الحقيقة،"
she's still watching these guys go; she says, "I can't ride a bike," no,
"وما زالت تنظر إلى المتجولين الآخرين، وقالت، "لا أستطيع ركوب الدراجة،" ، لا،
she says, "I can't use a skateboard, and I've never used roller blades,"
وقالت، "لا أستطيع ركوب سكيتبورد، ولم أجرب الرولر بليدز من قبل،"
she knew them by name;
كانت تعرفها بالاسم؛
she says, "And it's been 50 years since I rode a bicycle."
وقالت، "لم أركب الدراجة منذ 50 سنة."
Then she looks up, she's looking up, and she says,
ونظرت إليّ، وما زالت تنظر، وقالت،
"And I'm 81 years old, and I don't drive a car anymore.
"وعمري 81 سنة، ولم أعد أقود السيارة،
I still have to get to the store, and I can't carry a lot of things."
وما زلت بحاجة للذهاب إلى المتجر، وأعجز عن حمل الأغراض الكثيرة."
And it suddenly occurred to me, that among my many fears,
وخطر في قلبي فجأة، ضمن الأمور التي تخيفني،
were not just that the bureaucracy and the regulators
لم تكن فقط البيرقراطية والأنظمة
and the legislators might not get it --
والمشرعّين الذي لا يعون،
it was that, fundamentally, you believe there's pressure among the people
خطر في قلبي، أساساً، نؤمن أن هناك ضغط بين الناس
not to invade the most precious little bit of space left,
ألا نحتل المساحة الصغيرة الثمينة الباقية،
the sidewalks in these cities.
الأرصفة في هذه المدن.
When you look at the 36 inches of legal requirement for sidewalk,
حين تنظر إلى الـ36 بوصة الملزمة قانونياً للرصيف،
then the eight foot for the parked car, then the three lanes,
ثم إلى الثماني أقدام المخصصة للسيارة الواقفة، ثم إلى اللينات الثلاث للشارع
and then the other eight feet -- it's --
ثم ثماني أقدام أخرى -- إنها --
that little piece is all that's there.
ذلك الجزء الصغير هو كل ما لدينا.
But she looks up and says this,
ولكنها تنظر إليّ وتقول التالي،
and it occurs to me, well, kids aren't going to mind these things,
ويخطر في قلبي، في الحقيقة، الأطفال لن يمانعوا وجود هذه الأشياء،
and they don't vote, and business people and then young adults
وهم لا ينتخبون، ورجال الأعمال والمراهقين
aren't going to mind these things -- they're pretty cool --
لن يمانعوا وجود هذه الأشياء، إنه أمر جميل جداً،
so I guess subliminally I was worried
ولعلي كنت ضميناً قلِق
that it's the older population that's going to worry.
بأن كبار السن هم من سيقلق.
So, having seen this, and having worried about it for eight years,
لذلك، وبعد أن رأيت هذا، وقلقي لمدة ثماني سنوات،
the first thing I do is pick up my phone and ask our marketing and regulatory guys,
أول شيء فعلته هو الاتصال على موظفي التسويق والأنظمة وطلبت منهم،
call AARP, get an appointment right away.
الاتصال بـAARP، والحصول على موعد حالاً.
We've got to show them this thing.
لقد أتيناهم بهذا الشيء.
And they took it to Washington; they showed them;
وأخذوه إلى واشنطن، وأروهم،
and they're going to be involved now,
وسيكونون مشتركين معنا الآن،
watching how these things get absorbed in a number of cities,
وبمشاهدة امتصاص هذه الأشياء في بعض المدن
like Atlanta, where we're doing trials to see if it really can, in fact,
مثل آتلانتا، حيث كنا نقوم بتجاربنا لنرى كانت فعلاً، في الواقع،
help re-energize their downtown.
تساعد على ضخ الحياة في وسط مدينتهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The bottom line is, whether you believe the United Nations,
النقطة الأساسية هي، سواءً آمنت بالأمم المتحدة،
or any of the other think tanks --
أو أيٍ من مراكز الأبحاث الأخرى --
in the next 20 years, all human population growth on this planet
في العشرين سنة القادمة، جميع سكان هذا الكوكب
will be in cities.
سيقطنون المدن.
In Asia alone, it will be over a billion people.
في آسيا لوحدها، سيكون ما يزيد على مليار نسمة.
They learned to start with cell phones.
تعلموا على أن يبدأوا بالهواتف الخلوية.
They didn't have to take the 100-year trip we took.
لم يحتاجوا لمئة سنة من التنقل مثلنا.
They start at the top of the technology food chain.
بدأوا من رأس السلسلة التقنية.
We've got to start building cities and human environments
علينا أن نبدأ ببناء المدن والبيئات البشرية
where a 150-pound person can go a couple of miles
حيث يمكن لشخص يزن 150 رطل أن يتنقل لبضع أميال
in a dense, rich, green-space environment,
في بيئة كثيفة وغنية ومليئة بالمساحات الخضراء،
without being in a 4,000-pound machine to do it.
من غير حاجة إلى آلة تزن 4000 رطل.
Cars were not meant for parallel parking;
لم تُصنَع السيارات أبداً للوقوف الطولي؛
they're wonderful machines to go between cities, but just think about it:
إنها آلات جميلة للتنقل بين المدن، ولكن فكروا في الأمر:
we've solved all the long-range, high-speed problems.
حللنا كل مشاكل المسافات الطويلة والسرعات العالية.
The Greeks went from the theater of Dionysus to the Parthenon in their sandals.
كان اليونانيون يذهبون من مسرح ديونيسوس إلى البارثينون بنعلهم فقط.
You do it in your sneakers.
أنتم تفعلون ذلك بأحذيتكم الرياضية.
Not much has changed.
لم يتغير الكثير.
If this thing goes only three times as fast as walking -- three times --
إن كان هذا الشيء ينقلك بسرعة تزيد بثلاث أضعاف على سرعة مشيك -- ثلاث أضعاف --
a 30-minute walk becomes 10 minutes.
فإن مشي 30 دقيقة يتحول إلى 10 دقائق.
Your choice, when living in a city, if it's now 10 minutes --
خيارك، حين تعيش في المدينة، إن كان 10 دقائق الآن --
because at 30 minutes you want an alternative, whether it's a bus, a train --
لأنك في 30 دقيقة تيد خيار آخر، سواءً كان حافلةً أو قطاراً.
we've got to build an infrastructure -- a light rail --
علينا أن نبني البنية التحتية -- خط قطار خفيف --
or you're going to keep parking those cars.
أو نواصل إيقاف سياراتنا في المواقف.
But if you could put a pin in most cities,
ولكن إن وضعت دبوساً على معظم المدن (في الخريطة)،
and imagine how far you could, if you had the time, walk in one half-hour, it's the city.
وتخيلت المسافة التي ستقطعها، لو كان لديك الوقت، في مشيٍ لنصف ساعة، إنها المدينة.
If you could make it fun, and make it eight or 10 minutes,
لو استطعت أن تجعل الأمر ممتعاً، وتجعله 8 أو 10 دقائق،
you can't find your car, un-park your car, move your car,
لا تستطيع أن تجد سيارتك، تخرجها من الموقف، تحركها،
re-park your car and go somewhere;
تعيدها في المواقف، وتذهب إلى مكانٍ ما؛
you can't get to a cab or a subway.
لا تستطيع الحصول على تاكسي أو قطار.
We could change the way people allocate their resources,
يمكننا أن نغير طريقة توزيع الناس لمورادهم،
the way this planet uses its energy,
طريقة استهلاك الطاقة على هذا الكوكب،
make it more fun.
نجعلها أكثر متعة.
And we're hoping to some extent history will say we were right.
ونتمنى إلى حد ما أن يقول لنا التاريخ أننا كنا على حق.
That's Segway. This is a Stirling cycle engine;
هذه هي السيغوي. هذا محرك ستيرلينغ؛
this had been confused by a lot of things we're doing.
وقد تشوّش على البعض الكثير مما نفعله.
This little beast, right now, is producing a few hundred watts of electricity.
هذا الوحش الصغير، الآن، ينتج بضع مئات واط من الكهرباء.
Yes, it could be attached to this,
نعم، يمكننا أن نصلها بهذه،
and yes, on a kilogram of propane,
ونعم، بكيلوجرام من البروبان،
you could drive from New York to Boston if you so choose.
يمكنك أن تقودها من نيو يورك إلى بوسطن إن أردت.
Perhaps more interesting about this little engine is it'll burn any fuel,
ولعل المثير الاهتمام في هذا المحرك الصغير أنه يحرق جميع أنواع الوقود،
because some of you might be skeptical
لأن بعضكم قد يكون متشككاً
about the capability of this to have an impact,
حول قدرة هذه على التأثير،
where most of the world you can't simply plug into your 120-volt outlet.
حيث أنك في معظم العالم لا تستطيع أن تجد مقبس 120 فولت بسهولة.
We've been working on this,
عملنا حول هذه القضية،
actually, as an alternative energy source,
وفي الحقيقة، كمصدر بديل للطاقة،
starting way back with Johnson &amp; Johnson, to run an iBOT,
منذ عملنا مع جونسون آند جونسون، إلى تشغيل الآي بوت،
because the best batteries you could get --
لأن أفضل بطاريات يمكك أن تحصل عليها --
10 watt-hours per kilogram in lead,
10 واط-ساعات لكل كيلوجرام من الرصاص،
20 watt-hours per kilogram nickel-cadmium,
20 واط-ساعات لكل كيلوجرام من نيكل-كارديميوم،
40 watt-hours per kilogram in nickel-metal hydride,
40 واط-ساعات لكل كيلوجرام من نيكل-هايدرايد فلز،
60 watt-hours per kilogram in lithium,
60 واط-ساعات لكل كيلوجرام من الليثيوم،
8,750 watt-hours of energy in every kilogram of propane or gasoline --
8,750 واط-ساعات من الطاقة لكل كيلوجرام من البروبان أو البنزين --
which is why nobody drives electric cars.
لذلك لا أحد يقود سيارة كهربائية.
But, in any event, if you can burn it with the same efficiency --
ولكن، على أية حال، إن تمكنت من حرقها بنفس الفعالية --
because it's external combustion -- as your kitchen stove,
لأنه حرق خارجي -- مثل الفرن في المطبخ،
if you can burn any fuel, it turns out to be pretty neat.
إن تمكنت من حرق أي وقود، فإن الأمر يعدو جميلاً جداً.
It makes just enough electricity to, for instance, do this,
إنها تنتج ما يكفي من الكهرباء، مثلاً، افعل هذا،
which at night is enough electricity, in the rest of the world,
والذي يمثل خلال الليل، ما يكفي من الكهرباء، لبقيّة العالم
as Mr. Holly -- Dr. Holly -- pointed out,
كما لاحظ ذلك السيّد "هولي" --" د. هولي "،
can run computers and a light bulb.
يمكن أن يُشَغِّل حاسوبا و يضيء مصباحا.
But more interestingly, the thermodynamics of this say,
ولكن الأكثر أهميّة ، هو ما تُثبته الديناميكا الحرارية،
you're never going to get more than 20 percent efficiency.
وهو أنّ الفعاليّة التي سنحصل عليها لن تتجاوز 20 في المئة.
It doesn't matter much -- it says if you get 200 watts of electricity,
لا يهم كثيرا -- تقول انه اذا كان لديك 200 واط من الكهرباء ،
you'll get 700 or 800 watts of heat.
ستحصل على سبع أو ثماني مئة واط من الحرارة.
If you wanted to boil water and re-condense it at a rate of 10 gallons an hour,
إذا أردت غلي الماء وإعادة تكثيفه بمعدل 10 غالونات في السّاعة ،
it takes about 25, a little over 25.3 kilowatt --
سيستغرق الامر نحو 25 ، ما يزيد قليلا على 25.3 كيلو واط --
25,000 watts of continuous power -- to do it.
25000 واط من الطاقة المستمرّة -- للقيام بذلك.
That's so much energy, you couldn't afford to desalinate
وهذا يمثّل الكثير من الطاقة ، بحيث لا يمكن أن تنجح في تحلية
or clean water in this country that way.
أو تنظيف المياه في هذا البلد بهذه الطريقة.
Certainly, in the rest of the world, your choice is to devastate the place,
بالتأكيد ، في بقية العالم ، اختيارك هو تدمير المكان ،
turning everything that will burn into heat, or drink the water that's available.
تحول كل شيء سوف يحرق إلى حرارة ، أو شرب المياه المتاحة.
The number one cause of death on this planet among humans is bad water.
سبب الوفاة الأوّل على هذا الكوكب بين البشر هي المياه السيئة النوعيّة.
Depending on whose numbers you believe,
اعتمادا على الأرقام التي تثق بها،
it's between 60 and 85,000 people per day.
إنّها ما بين 60 و 85000 شخص يوميا.
We don't need sophisticated heart transplants around the world.
لا نحتاج الى عمليات زرع القلب المتطورة في جميع أنحاء العالم.
We need water.
نحن بحاجة إلى الماء.
And women shouldn't have to spend four hours a day looking for it,
ولا ينبغي للنساء قضاء أربع ساعات يوميا في البحث عنه،
or watching their kids die.
أو مشاهدة أطفالهم يموتون.
We figured out how to put a vapor-compression distiller on this thing,
لقد نجحنا في وضع قَطَّارٍ بخاريّ مضغوط على هذا الشيء ،
with a counter-flow heat exchanger to take the waste heat,
مع مبادل حراري مكافح للتدفق للحفاظ على الحرارة الضائعة،
then using a little bit of the electricity control that process,
ثم باستخدام القليل من الكهرباء للسّيطرة على تلك العملية ،
and for 450 watts, which is a little more than half of its waste heat,
وباستعمال 450 واط ، وهو ما يزيد قليلا على نصف الحرارة الضائعة،
it will make 10 gallons an hour of distilled water
سوف تنتج 10 غالون من الماء المقطر في السّاعة
from anything that comes into it to cool it.
ممّا وضعناه فيها لنُبَرِّدَهُ.
So if we put this box on here in a few years,
لذلك إذا وضعنا هذا الصندوق هنا في غضون سنوات قليلة،
could we have a solution to transportation, electricity,
ربما سيكون لدينا حَلٌّ للنّقل و الكهرباء ،
and communication, and maybe drinkable water
والاتصالات ، وربّما المياه الصالحة للشرب
in a sustainable package that weighs 60 pounds?
في حزمة مستدامة تزن 60 باوندا؟
I don't know, but we'll try it.
أنا لا أعرف ، ولكن سنحاول القيام بذلك.
I better shut up.
سيكون من الأفضل أن أصمت.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)